Guide to the Gladys Campbell Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Gladys Campbell papers
1914-1995
YCAL MSS 251
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.25
(5 boxes)
The Gladys Campbell Papers contain correspondence, writings, and other papers that document the work of the poet Gladys Campbell and other members of the University of Chicago Poetry Club, as well as her relationships with other poets. The papers also contain writings of George Dillon, Charles Bell, Janet Lewis, Maurice Lesemann, Naomi Clark, and Morton Zabel. The papers span the years 1914 to 1995.
Campbell, Gladys, 1892-1992
Bell, Charles G. (Charles Greenleaf), 1916-2010
Clark, Naomi
Dillon, George, 1906-1968
Lesemann, Maurice, 1899-
Wescott, Glenway, 1901-1987
Zabel, Morton Dauwen, 1901-1964
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Serendipity Books on the Elizabeth Wakeman Dwight Memorial Fund, 2003.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Gladys Campbell
Gladys Campbell (1892-1992) attended the University of Chicago to study poetry and earned a Bachelor of Arts in 1920 and a Master of Arts in 1943. Campbell was one of the early members of the University of Chicago Poetry Club, a group formed in 1917 by students who wished to address the absence of modern poetry in the University curriculum. Other members included Glenway Wescott, George Dillon, Elizabeth Madox Roberts, Arthur Yvor Winters, Llewellyn Jones, Maurice Lesemann, and Janet Lewis. Harriet Monroe, the founder and editor of Poetry Magazine, visited the group often.
Gladys Campbell and George Dillon (1906-1968) were editors of the Poetry Club's publication, The Forge: A Journal of Verse, published from 1924 to 1929. Campbell and Dillon were close friends for their entire lives and Dillon sent his poems to her for criticism. He was the editor for Poetry Magazine from 1937 to 1949, during which time he also served in WWII. Another close friend of Gladys Campbell's was the writer Glenway Wescott (1901-1987). Charles Bell (1916-), another poet and Assistant Professor of Humanities at the University of Chicago, also sent Campbell drafts of poems for criticism.
Campbell wrote poetry throughout her life and her poems appeared frequently in Poetry, The Forge, The Dial and Book Notes. She published one collection, The Momentary Beach, in 1972. From 1922 to 1929, Campbell taught English in the University of Chicago Lab Schools and from 1929 to 1957 she taught humanities and English at the University of Chicago. She retired in 1957. Campbell was active in Hyde Park's Poetry Society, which met in her apartment. Writers such as Yvor Winters, George Dillon, and Thornton Wilder were among its members. Campbell never married and lived in the Hyde Park section of Chicago until her death in 1992.
Scope and Contents
The Gladys Campbell Papers contain correspondence, writings, and other papers that document the work of the poet Gladys Campbell and friends from the University of Chicago Poetry Club, as well as her relationship with other poets. The papers also contain writings of George Dillon, Charles Bell, Janet Lewis, Maurice Lesemann, Naomi Clark, and Morton Zabel. The papers span the years 1914 to 1995. Correspondence comprises the bulk of the papers and spans 1914 to 1995. Writings by Gladys Campbell and others spans 1924 to 1986 and includes undated material. Photographs and printed materials make up the smallest portion of the papers, spanning 1924 to 1992.
Arrangement
The Gladys Campbell Papers are organized into six series: Correspondence, Writings, Writings of Others, Photographs, University of Chicago Materials, and Printed Materials.
Dial (Chicago, Ill.); Forge (Chicago, Ill.); Poetry (Chicago, Ill.); American poetry -- 20th Century; Poets, American -- 20th Century; Poets; Adler, Mortimer Jerome, 1902-2001; Bell, Charles G. (Charles Greenleaf), 1916-2010; Campbell, Gladys, 1892-1992; Campbell, Kathleen; Clark, Naomi; Dillon, George, 1906-1968; Hill, Knox C.; Hughes, Langston, 1902-1967; Lesemann, Maurice, 1899-; Levi, Edward H. (Edward Hirsch), 1911-2000; Lewis, Janet, 1899-1998; Monroe, Harriet, 1860-1936; Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972; Rago, Henry, 1915-1969; Roberts, Elizabeth Madox, 1881-1941; Slavick, William H.; Wescott, Glenway, 1901-1987; Wilder, Thornton, 1897-1975; Zabel, Morton Dauwen, 1901-1964; Charles Scribner's Sons; Modern Poetry Association; University of Chicago; University of Chicago. Poetry Club
- Correspondence, 1914-1995; Series I; 2.7; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I, Correspondence, is arranged alphabetically by correspondent, with a small amount of third party and unidentified correspondence filed at the end. Correspondence from friends upon the receipt of Campbell's book of poetry, Momentary Beach is grouped together at the end of the series.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains correspondence between Gladys Campbell and a number of her friends. The primary correspondents are George Dillon and Glenway Wescott; they discuss Gladys Campbell's and their own poetry throughout their correspondence. Correspondence from George Dillon Janet Lewis includes drafts of their poems.
  George Dillon's letters document his decision to work for Poetry Magazine as Associate Editor and his dedication to The Forge, as well as proposed changes to be made to Poetry Magazine under his leadership.
  - Adler, Mortimer, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Boulton, Inez, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Campbell, Kathleen Foster, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Carpenter, Margaret, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes two photographs of George Dillon and photocopy of Dillon's obituary
  - DeVries, Peter, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Dial, 1925-1929 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dillon, George, 1924-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 7-23)
    Includes typescript drafts of George Dillon poems:
    "Again"
    "Autumn Wind"
    "A Day of Rain,"
    "From Happiness Once"
    "At John Keet's Grave"
    "Old Masonry"
    "Sonnet"
    "The Summer Sea"
  - Dillon, George, 1942-68 (Box 2, Folder 24-29)
  - Dillon, George, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Includes typescript draft of George Dillon poem "The Pomegranate" and drawing of Gladys Campbell by George Dillon enclosed with undated letter
  - Flint, Edith Foster, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Gerson, Noel, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Harrison, Gilbert, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Hill, Knox, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Hughes, Langston, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Gilbert, Jim, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Hutchins, Robert, 1940-1951, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Kreymbord, Alfred, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Lesemann, Maurice, 1929-1934, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Levi, Edward, 1968-1971 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Lewis, Janet, circa 1925, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
    General note
    Includes a signed photocopy of Lewis's "For Emily" and printouts of "For Esther Sills" and "For Clara Atkins on her 91 Birthday."
  - Lovett, Robert
    See: University of Chicago
  - Masters, Marcia, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - The Modern Poetry Association, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Monroe, Harriet
    See: Poetry Magazine
  - Moore, Marianne
    See: The Dial
  - Poetry Magazine, 1929-1935 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Rich, Daniel Catton, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Roberts, Elizabeth Madox, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Russ, Elmo, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Charles Scribner's Sons, 1927, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Slavick, William, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Stevenson, Ellen Borden
    See: The Modern Poetry Association
  - Toigo, John, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - University of Chicago, 1917-1957 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Wescott, Glenway, 1919-1922, undated (Box 2, Folder 52-53)
  - Wilder, Thornton, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Wilder, Isabel and Janet, 1934, 1972, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Windeyer, Lt. Colonel R.C., 1915 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Zabel, Morton, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Correspondence regarding Momentary Beach, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 58-59)
  - Unidentified correspondence, 1914, undated (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Third party correspondence
    - Bell, Charles to George Dillon, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Lewis, Janet to Kathleen Foster Campbell, 1978, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Lewis, Janet to Hugh Tinker, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 63)
- Writings, undated; Series II; 4
  Series II, Writings, contains three groups of poems by Gladys Campbell. The first, labeled by Campbell "Good copies of most best poems," is numbered in order, perhaps in preparation for a book. The second, an intended compilation titled The Shadowed Field, includes poems previously published in Poetry, The Dial, The Forge and Book Notes. The third group is comprised of unpublished poems that Campbell labeled "unpub". The series also includes an "Inventory" of Campbell's teaching, writings and publications.
  - "Good copies of most of best poems," drafts, typescript and holograph, undated (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - The Shadowed Field, draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - "Unpub," drafts, typescript and holograph, corrected, undated (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - "Inventory of Individual Work," completed form, undated (Box 3, Folder 67)
- Writings of Others, 1924-1986; Series III; 0.3; (.75 box)
  Series III, Writings of Others, is arranged alphabetically by author, with "The Poetry Club of Chicago: Bibliography (Early, Major, Collected)" filed at the end.
  This series contains writings by Gladys Campbell's friends and fellow members of the University of Chicago Poetry Club, who sent their writings to Campbell for criticism. The bulk is poems by George Dillon, although Glenway Wescott's and Charles Bell's writings are also substantial. Bell's writings often include notes to Campbell in the margins.
  - Charles, Bell
    - Poems, drafts, holograph and typescript carbon, 1973, undated (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - "A Scene from Faust," draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Clark, Naomi. "Late Autumnal: California" and "Variations on a Theme Dream" drafts, typescript and typescript photocopy, undated (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Dillon, George. Poems, drafts, holograph and typescript, annotated, 1924, undated (Box 3, Folder 71-73)
    Includes "To Gladys, A Simplicity"
    See: Dillon, George
  - Lewis, Janet. Poems, drafts, typescript, annotated, 1980-1986, undated (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Lesemann, Maurice. "The Gale" draft, typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Wescott, Glenway
    - "I, In My Pitiful Flesh" and "After-Image," drafts, holograph corrected, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - "A Lonely Fire," draft, typescript carbon, undated (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Zabel, Morton Dauwen, "Herakles Archer," draft, typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - "The Poetry Club of Chicago: Bibliography (Early, Major, Collected)," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 3, Folder 79)
- Photographs, 1918-1983; Series IV; 5
  Series IV, Photographs, is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Campbell, Gladys, circa 1957 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Campbell, Gladys and Jim Gilbert, undated (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Dillon, George, 1918, circa 1940, undated (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Lewis, Janet, circa 1983 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Wescott, Glenway, circa 1920 (Box 4, Folder 84)
- University of Chicago Materials, 1923-1955; Series V; 4
  Series V, University of Chicago Materials, is arranged chronologically
  This series includes material relating to Gladys Campbell's work as a student and faculty member at the University of Chicago.
  - "Fennel Stalks," a publication by the students in the University of Chicago High School at the University of Chicago, dedicated to Gladys Campbell, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - Diploma, The University of Chicago, Master of Arts, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 86)
    Includes typescript of Honor Schedules, Spring Semester
  - "The University of Chicago First Year Course of Study of Humanities, Syllabus for the First Year Course in the College", September 1943 (Box 4, Folder 87)
  - "An Introduction to the Humanities, A Discussion Manual" prepared by members of the humanities staff of the College of the University of Chicago, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 88)
- Printed Material, 1930-1992, undated; Series VI; 0.1
  Series VI, Printed Material, is arranged chronologically.
  This series includes journal reprints, holiday cards, reports, clippings, and a brochure.
  - Illustrated Christmas card with Edna St. Vincent Millay passage, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - "The Pattern of Proustian Love," by Milton Hindus, autographed reprint from New Mexico Quarterly, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 90)
  - "'Crime and Punishment' as Philosophy," by Knox C. Hill, autographed reprint from The Journal of General Education, January 1953 (Box 4, Folder 91)
  - "Report to the Trustees of the Modern Poetry Association History and Summary of Activities, 1912-1950" and "Recent Reports to the Bollingen Foundation," typescript carbon, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 92)
  - Illustrated autographed cards by Juliet and Henry Rago, 1957, undated (Box 4, Folder 93)
  - "First Comments from Teachers on Three Plays of Racine (excerpts from letters, October 1961)," typescript (Box 4, Folder 94)
    Includes excerpt from George Bell
  - "A Note on George Dillon," by Nicholas Joost with poems translated by Dillon, from Delta Epsilon Sigma Bulletin, March 1962 (Box 4, Folder 95)
  - Elizabeth Madox Roberts Centenary Conference, brochure and conference attendees list, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 96)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1992, undated (Box 4, Folder 97)
    Gladys Campbell and Joanna Fortune at Poetry luncheon; on George Dillon's death with poem "Anatomy of Death;" and Poetry's 80 year anniversary
- Oversize
  - Drawing of Gladys Campbell by George Dillon (Series I), undated (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 98)